<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>SFPE Central VA</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/</id><updated>2020-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Joe Rainey</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/joe-rainey.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-08-06:/sfpecva/joe-rainey.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Joe is a fire protection engineer at Moseley Architects, an A/E firm providing comprehensive professional architectural, engineering, and interior design solutions for a wide variety of building and facility types. He provides fire protection systems design for facilities and is involved with the process from proposal through construction. Joe …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Joe is a fire protection engineer at Moseley Architects, an A/E firm providing comprehensive professional architectural, engineering, and interior design solutions for a wide variety of building and facility types. He provides fire protection systems design for facilities and is involved with the process from proposal through construction. Joe grew up in Richmond and studied Mechanical Engineering at VCU, and later earned his PE in fire protection in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Officers"></category></entry><entry><title>Philip Pyron</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/philip-pyron.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-08-05:/sfpecva/philip-pyron.html</id><content type="html"></content><category term="Officers"></category></entry><entry><title>Laura Woody</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/laura-woody.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-08-04:/sfpecva/laura-woody.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Laura has been involved with the SFPE chapter for almost 30 years. She says the education and networking at SFPE chapter meetings has been significant in increasing her job effectiveness and advancing her career. She retired in June 2016 (but continues to be involved with SFPE) after 36 years with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Laura has been involved with the SFPE chapter for almost 30 years. She says the education and networking at SFPE chapter meetings has been significant in increasing her job effectiveness and advancing her career. She retired in June 2016 (but continues to be involved with SFPE) after 36 years with FM Global, one of the world’s largest commercial and industrial property insurance companies. She holds a professional engineer license in fire protection, which she credits SFPE with helping her obtain.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Officers"></category></entry><entry><title>Andrea Schumaker</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/andrea-schumaker.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-08-03:/sfpecva/andrea-schumaker.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Andrea has worked completed plan review and inspections for fire protection plans and building plans related to International Building Codes and Life Safety Codes in Maryland and Virginia. Career focus for 20 + years has been working in the highly protected risk (HPR) commercial property insurance industry. Experience includes plan review …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Andrea has worked completed plan review and inspections for fire protection plans and building plans related to International Building Codes and Life Safety Codes in Maryland and Virginia. Career focus for 20 + years has been working in the highly protected risk (HPR) commercial property insurance industry. Experience includes plan review, witnessing field acceptance testing, risk assessment and analysis for industrial and commercial business operations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Officers"></category></entry><entry><title>Brian Cohan</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/brian-cohan.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-08-02:/sfpecva/brian-cohan.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Brian is a senior consultant working in nuclear fire protection at Appendix R Solutions. He works on fire probabilistic risk assessments for commercial plants and focuses on the detailed fire modeling aspect. In addition to performing the analyses for the plants, he develops and maintains the tools required to do …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Brian is a senior consultant working in nuclear fire protection at Appendix R Solutions. He works on fire probabilistic risk assessments for commercial plants and focuses on the detailed fire modeling aspect. In addition to performing the analyses for the plants, he develops and maintains the tools required to do the work. Brian graduated from the University of Maryland in 2008 and 2010 with bachelors and masters in Fire Protection Engineering and received his Professional Engineer (PE) credential in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Officers"></category></entry><entry><title>Bryan Powell</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/bryan-powell.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-08-01:/sfpecva/bryan-powell.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bryan is a senior loss prevention consultant for GAP Services and has been an active member in the Central Virginia Chapter of the SFPE since 1987. He received the designation “Certified Fire Protection Specialist” from the NFPA in 1995 and received his Professional Engineer (PE) credential in January 2004.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Officers"></category></entry><entry><title>April Meeting Topic To Be Determined</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/april-meeting-topic-to-be-determined.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-27T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-27T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-04-27:/sfpecva/april-meeting-topic-to-be-determined.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Check back later for more information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>March Meeting Topic To Be Determined</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/march-meeting-topic-to-be-determined.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-01T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-01T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-03-01:/sfpecva/march-meeting-topic-to-be-determined.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Check back later for more information.  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>February Meeting Topic To Be Determined</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/february-meeting-topic-to-be-determined.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-24T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-24T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2020-02-24:/sfpecva/february-meeting-topic-to-be-determined.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Check back later for more information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Self-Regulating Variable Speed Fire Pump Units</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/self-regulating-variable-speed-fire-pump-units.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-25T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-25T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2019-11-25:/sfpecva/self-regulating-variable-speed-fire-pump-units.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Currently, Steven has the title of Marketing Manager – Fire Products for the Building System Solutions Group at Armstrong Fluid Technology. In this role, Steven provides leadership to product development, and business strategy of the Global Armstrong Fire business. Prior to joining Armstrong in 2008, Steven held various product management roles …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Currently, Steven has the title of Marketing Manager – Fire Products for the Building System Solutions Group at Armstrong Fluid Technology. In this role, Steven provides leadership to product development, and business strategy of the Global Armstrong Fire business. Prior to joining Armstrong in 2008, Steven held various product management roles for an electrical supply and distribution equipment manufacturer. He has participated with numerous industry associations, and holds a degree in Electrical Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steven Baird
Armstrong Fluid Technology&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Red Flags of Fire-Stopping</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/red-flags-of-fire-stopping.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-28T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-28T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2019-10-28:/sfpecva/red-flags-of-fire-stopping.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Anna
Hilti&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Nitrogen Generator for dry and pre-action sprinkler system</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/nitrogen-generator-for-dry-and-pre-action-sprinkler-system.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-23T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-23T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2019-09-23:/sfpecva/nitrogen-generator-for-dry-and-pre-action-sprinkler-system.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Parking is available on the street and in the parking lot. Come into the building at the interior corner with the canopy right off the grassy courtyard where the brick portion meets the metal portion (see picture on page 3 along with map in attached meeting announcement). Ring doorbell on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Parking is available on the street and in the parking lot. Come into the building at the interior corner with the canopy right off the grassy courtyard where the brick portion meets the metal portion (see picture on page 3 along with map in attached meeting announcement). Ring doorbell on the right side to be let in and we will have someone bring you to the conference room from the main lobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack Coffelt
Business Development Manger
Potter Electric Signaling Co.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>SFPE Central VA Social</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/sfpe-central-va-social.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-20T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-20T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2019-05-20:/sfpecva/sfpe-central-va-social.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This meeting we are going to take it easy and just try to spend more time getting to know each other. Come to Mekong and just enjoy hanging out and networking. Of course there will be a few small business items to attend to including seeing if anyone is interested …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This meeting we are going to take it easy and just try to spend more time getting to know each other. Come to Mekong and just enjoy hanging out and networking. Of course there will be a few small business items to attend to including seeing if anyone is interested in joining the board. Some hors d'oeuvres will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Tall Wood Buildings: Feasibility, Testing, and Proposals for Code Changes</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/tall-wood-buildings-feasibility-testing-and-proposals-for-code-changes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-04-22T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-22T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2019-04-22:/sfpecva/tall-wood-buildings-feasibility-testing-and-proposals-for-code-changes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In early 2016, the ICC Board of Directors approved the creation of an ad hoc committee to explore the building science of tall wood buildings with the scope being to investigate the feasibility of and take action to develop code changes for tall wood buildings. Since that time, the Tall …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In early 2016, the ICC Board of Directors approved the creation of an ad hoc committee to explore the building science of tall wood buildings with the scope being to investigate the feasibility of and take action to develop code changes for tall wood buildings. Since that time, the Tall Wood Building (TWB) Ad Hoc Committee has reviewed voluminous materials regarding tall wood buildings, including results of various testing around the world, as well as studies domestically in support of the TWB charge to conduct a thorough review of the science of tall wood. The TWB developed its own test scenario(s) to substantiate any code change proposals (testing was carried out at ATF labs); and worked to develop a comprehensive set of technically-substantiated code changes for consideration during the 2018 Group A code development process. The intensive research performed by the Committee was submitted under the ICC Code Development Process, along with the resulting proposals developed by Committee consensus. All of the Group A TWB proposals have been approved. The TWB has also developed a set of Group B proposals, submitted in January 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raymond O’Brocki
CBO, Manager of Fire Service Relations
American Wood Council&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Elevator Sprinklers and Detectors: Who Wants What, Where, and Why?</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/elevator-sprinklers-and-detectors-who-wants-what-where-and-why.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-25T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-25T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2019-03-25:/sfpecva/elevator-sprinklers-and-detectors-who-wants-what-where-and-why.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An exploration of the intersection of four codes and standards: The Elevator Code (ASME A17.1), the Building Code (IBC), NFPA 13, and NFPA 72, this presentation will go through the requirements of each as it relates to when to provide sprinklers and detection, and when to omit them, and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An exploration of the intersection of four codes and standards: The Elevator Code (ASME A17.1), the Building Code (IBC), NFPA 13, and NFPA 72, this presentation will go through the requirements of each as it relates to when to provide sprinklers and detection, and when to omit them, and go through the commentary to explain the reasoning behind the requirements. With four different codes and standards to coordinate, what could go wrong?! Joe has 10 years of experience in fire protection engineering, and has been involved in SFPE for much of that time. Prior to that he graduated from VCU with a degree in mechanical engineering at VCU and had no idea what fire protection engineering was. Joe enjoys playing music, golf, and overly-complicated board games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Rainey
Moseley Architects&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>2015 IBC Chapter 7 “Fire and Smoke Protection Features” with current Virginia Amendments</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/2015-ibc-chapter-7-fire-and-smoke-protection-features-with-current-virginia-amendments.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-25T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-25T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2019-02-25:/sfpecva/2015-ibc-chapter-7-fire-and-smoke-protection-features-with-current-virginia-amendments.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fire-resistance-rated construction is one form of fire protection in building design and is often referred to as “passive protection.” Fire-resistance-rated building elements provide “passive” resistance to the advance of fire, as opposed to “active” fire protection systems, such as automatic sprinkler systems, which actively attempt to suppress a fire. Chapter …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fire-resistance-rated construction is one form of fire protection in building design and is often referred to as “passive protection.” Fire-resistance-rated building elements provide “passive” resistance to the advance of fire, as opposed to “active” fire protection systems, such as automatic sprinkler systems, which actively attempt to suppress a fire. Chapter 7 provides detailed requirements for this “passive” approach. This presentation will explore how various elements are constructed and how openings and penetrations are protected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kenney Payne
Dean of Moseley University, Quality Control, Risk Management, and Training
Moseley Architects&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Firefighting and fire protection challenges of automated warehouse storage systems.</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/firefighting-and-fire-protection-challenges-of-automated-warehouse-storage-systems.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-28T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-28T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2019-01-28:/sfpecva/firefighting-and-fire-protection-challenges-of-automated-warehouse-storage-systems.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Automated storage retrieval systems using robots powered by batteries that pull orders from tightly spaced bins limit the flue spaces and aisles that fire protection engineers are accustom to. Even though sprinkler operations can be satisfactory, final extinguishment by firefighters has proven to be difficult. Some public fire brigades have …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Automated storage retrieval systems using robots powered by batteries that pull orders from tightly spaced bins limit the flue spaces and aisles that fire protection engineers are accustom to. Even though sprinkler operations can be satisfactory, final extinguishment by firefighters has proven to be difficult. Some public fire brigades have stated that they will not attempt to fight such a fire unless people are trapped in the building. These fires can be fought successfully, but they require planning. The presenter has fought such a fire as a firefighter and has also been part of numerous full-scale fire tests at UL. Insights and lessons learned will be presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Frank
Loss Prevention Center of Excellence Leader
AXA XL Risk Consulting&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Firestop 101 – Firestopping: A Life Safety Issue</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/firestop-101-firestopping-a-life-safety-issue.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-19T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-19T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2018-11-19:/sfpecva/firestop-101-firestopping-a-life-safety-issue.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A seminar presenting the key test standards related to firestopping in applicable codes, the variables that affect firestop performance, and the secondary attributes of firestop products. How to improve your specifications, drawings and details to promote proper selection and quality installation of firestop systems. Jason is the dedicated technical representative …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A seminar presenting the key test standards related to firestopping in applicable codes, the variables that affect firestop performance, and the secondary attributes of firestop products. How to improve your specifications, drawings and details to promote proper selection and quality installation of firestop systems. Jason is the dedicated technical representative for Hilti in the state of Virginia. He provides technical support on applications relating to anchoring/fastening, firestop, and installation (strut) systems, and consultative services regarding Building Codes, ASTM/UL Test Standards, UL Firestop Systems &amp;amp; Assemblies, Engineering Judgments, and specification &amp;amp; plan review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Anna
Technical Representative
Hilti&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>F-500 Encapsulator Agent Fire Suppression Technology</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/f-500-encapsulator-agent-fire-suppression-technology.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-22T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-22T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2018-10-22:/sfpecva/f-500-encapsulator-agent-fire-suppression-technology.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;HCT’s F-500 Encapsulator Agent’s engineered advantage is based on the high performance, three-dimensional firefighting capabilities of micelle encapsulation. This combination of attributes provides for quick knockdown and rapid heat reduction, providing permanent burnback resistance. F-500 encapsulates hydrocarbon liquids and vapors rendering fuel non-flammable and non-ignitable while interrupting free …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;HCT’s F-500 Encapsulator Agent’s engineered advantage is based on the high performance, three-dimensional firefighting capabilities of micelle encapsulation. This combination of attributes provides for quick knockdown and rapid heat reduction, providing permanent burnback resistance. F-500 encapsulates hydrocarbon liquids and vapors rendering fuel non-flammable and non-ignitable while interrupting free radical coalescence, inhibiting the formation of toxic soot and smoke. All of this leads to enhanced firefighting performance with increased life safety and reduced property damage while minimizing water use and the subsequent water damage and runoff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Thompson
Encapsulator Technology Specialist
Hazard Control Technologies, Inc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>The Effect of Obstructed Ceiling Construction on Automatic Sprinkler Protection</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/the-effect-of-obstructed-ceiling-construction-on-automatic-sprinkler-protection.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-24T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-24T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2018-09-24:/sfpecva/the-effect-of-obstructed-ceiling-construction-on-automatic-sprinkler-protection.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;NFPA 13 and FM Global Loss Prevention Data Sheet 2-0 provide guidance on how to install Control Mode sprinklers in the presence of obstructed ceiling construction, but the installation guidelines for Suppression Mode sprinklers in the presence of obstructed ceiling construction is much more stringent. Historically there has been very …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NFPA 13 and FM Global Loss Prevention Data Sheet 2-0 provide guidance on how to install Control Mode sprinklers in the presence of obstructed ceiling construction, but the installation guidelines for Suppression Mode sprinklers in the presence of obstructed ceiling construction is much more stringent. Historically there has been very little test data or modeling analysis to support the installation guidelines currently available for Suppression Mode sprinklers protecting a storage environment. This presentation will discuss the current installation guidelines for sprinklers protecting storage in the presence of obstructed ceiling construction, recent numerical computer modeling conducted by FM Global to investigate the principal effects of obstructed ceiling construction on sprinkler activation, as well as large-scale fire testing that was conducted by FM Global based on the results obtained through computer modeling. Wes is a member of the Society of Fire Protection Engineers and an NFPA member serving on both the NFPA 13 Installation and NFPA 13 Discharge committees. Wes has been with FM Global for over 33 years and is currently responsible for data sheets related to the protection of storage, as well as the installation guidelines for sprinklers that are used for storage protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weston (Wes) C Baker Jr
Senior Engineering Technical Specialist, in the Engineering Standards division
FM Global&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Safespill systems</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/safespill-systems.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-21T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-21T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2018-05-21:/sfpecva/safespill-systems.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Spill containment and removal system delivering a completely new and safe way to store any ignitable liquid in totes or drums, allowing spilled liquids to be safely removed to an external containment tank through an integrated flushing and suction system. Go to http://www.safespillsystems.com/spill-and-fire-tests to learn more …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Spill containment and removal system delivering a completely new and safe way to store any ignitable liquid in totes or drums, allowing spilled liquids to be safely removed to an external containment tank through an integrated flushing and suction system. Go to http://www.safespillsystems.com/spill-and-fire-tests to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam Bowen
Director of Business Development
Safespill Systems&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Fire Protection in Data Centers, Computer Equipment Areas, and Energy Storage Systems</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/fire-protection-in-data-centers-computer-equipment-areas-and-energy-storage-systems.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-23T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-23T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2018-04-23:/sfpecva/fire-protection-in-data-centers-computer-equipment-areas-and-energy-storage-systems.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nick Johnson is a research engineer in 3M™ Company’s Electronic Material Solutions Division, working the fluoro-chemicals lab. He provides technical support for Novec™ 1230 and is directly involved in new fire protection applications as well as vetting of new novel fluids with potential as future fire suppression agents. Over …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nick Johnson is a research engineer in 3M™ Company’s Electronic Material Solutions Division, working the fluoro-chemicals lab. He provides technical support for Novec™ 1230 and is directly involved in new fire protection applications as well as vetting of new novel fluids with potential as future fire suppression agents. Over the past five years, Nick’s research has been focused on thermal management of lithium ion batteries and mitigating the potential of cascading thermal runaway within such batteries. He holds a Bachelor’s of Science in Mechanical Engineering from the University of St. Thomas and is an alternate on the developing NFPA 855: Standard for the Installation of Stationary Energy Storage Systems and a liaison member of SAE G27: Lithium Battery Packaging Performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick Johson
Research Engineer
Electronics Materials Solutions Division 3M&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Fire Pump Room Issues</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/fire-pump-room-issues.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-14T11:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-14T11:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2018-03-14:/sfpecva/fire-pump-room-issues.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my 20 plus years of inspecting and testing fire pumps, you always think - Well I have seen it all now. Only to find you have not seen it all. We will go over a few of the more strange fire pump applications and the impact they could have on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my 20 plus years of inspecting and testing fire pumps, you always think - Well I have seen it all now. Only to find you have not seen it all. We will go over a few of the more strange fire pump applications and the impact they could have on the system. The fire pump is the heart of the sprinkler system. Without it, it’s like our bodies - the rest of the system won't work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill Jones
President
FirePro, Inc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Foam Suppression Systems</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/foam-suppression-systems.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-26T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-26T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2018-02-26:/sfpecva/foam-suppression-systems.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An overview of the different types of foams, foam delivery systems, key required equipment, and the applications for each type of foam suppression system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Troy Wiltbank
Business Development, Fire Suppression Products
Johnson Controls&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Fire Door Inspections &amp; Field Labeling</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/fire-door-inspections-field-labeling.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-16T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-16T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2018-01-16:/sfpecva/fire-door-inspections-field-labeling.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like other fire resistance rated construction materials under the purview of the U.S. system of codes and standards, fire doors have more than a century’s worth of testing experience published in the various listing directories made available for reference in project specifications. This testing and listing experience provides …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like other fire resistance rated construction materials under the purview of the U.S. system of codes and standards, fire doors have more than a century’s worth of testing experience published in the various listing directories made available for reference in project specifications. This testing and listing experience provides a level of confidence for door manufacturers, insurance underwriters, design professionals and approving governmental authorities that a particular door assembly has undergone stringent testing protocol, and that it can be expected to curtail losses associated with a given building fire event. By looking at the historic development of building codes and test standards related to this specific component, it is helpful to determine what has shaped the current fire door industry and better evaluate future trends in listing and labeling provisions including the increasing use of field-labeling for existing applications. This is a great challenge of compliance that Facility Managers, and Authorities Having Jurisdiction are now facing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justin Biller
Owner, Principal Fire Protection Engineer
Emerson Graham + Associates&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>HI-FOG® Water Mist Fire Protection System</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/hi-fogr-water-mist-fire-protection-system.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-20T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-20T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2017-11-20:/sfpecva/hi-fogr-water-mist-fire-protection-system.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An environmentally friendly way to reduce fire, smoke and water damage with minimal business interruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lorraine Smith
Vertical Sales Manager
Marioff&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Viking Vacuum Style Dry Valve and New Sprinklers</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/viking-vacuum-style-dry-valve-and-new-sprinklers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-23T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-23T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2017-10-23:/sfpecva/viking-vacuum-style-dry-valve-and-new-sprinklers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This summer and Fall Viking has released several new sprinkler heads along with the new Vactec system with Fire Flex. This is the first vacuum style dry valve listed for fire protection. We will also be introducing some new products this fall for our special hazards division as well with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This summer and Fall Viking has released several new sprinkler heads along with the new Vactec system with Fire Flex. This is the first vacuum style dry valve listed for fire protection. We will also be introducing some new products this fall for our special hazards division as well with more sprinkler heads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bryan Berkley
National Technical Representative
Viking Corporation&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Special Effects: Pyrotechnics, Flame Effects, Smoke, Lasers, and More!</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/special-effects-pyrotechnics-flame-effects-smoke-lasers-and-more.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-25T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-25T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2017-09-25:/sfpecva/special-effects-pyrotechnics-flame-effects-smoke-lasers-and-more.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Introduction to special effects used during theatrical performances and before a proximate audience. A brief description of special effects types and an overview of product design, set-up and safety aspects will be provided. Steven currently serves as the Virginia State Fire Marshal’s Office Compliance Officer. He is responsible for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Introduction to special effects used during theatrical performances and before a proximate audience. A brief description of special effects types and an overview of product design, set-up and safety aspects will be provided. Steven currently serves as the Virginia State Fire Marshal’s Office Compliance Officer. He is responsible for Special Operations of the SFMO. One major component of Special Operations is the explosives enforcement program. He has worked in emergency services for over 26 years. and served in a fire marshal role for 18 of the 26 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steven Sites
Virginia State Fire Marshal's Office&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Protection of Mini-Load Automatic Storage and Retrieval System (ASRS)</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/protection-of-mini-load-automatic-storage-and-retrieval-system-asrs.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-22T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2017-05-22:/sfpecva/protection-of-mini-load-automatic-storage-and-retrieval-system-asrs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The presentation will cover an overview of the different types of ASRS systems, the research project on mini-load systems, and a preview of what changes are coming in the revised FM Global Data Sheet 8-34, Protection for Automatic Storage and Retrieval Systems, which will be released in July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brent …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The presentation will cover an overview of the different types of ASRS systems, the research project on mini-load systems, and a preview of what changes are coming in the revised FM Global Data Sheet 8-34, Protection for Automatic Storage and Retrieval Systems, which will be released in July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brent Wunderlich
Operations Chief Engineer
FM Global&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Overview of the State Fire Marshal’s Office and Statewide Fire Prevention Code Adoption Process and Issues</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/overview-of-the-state-fire-marshals-office-and-statewide-fire-prevention-code-adoption-process-and-issues.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-24T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-24T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2017-04-24:/sfpecva/overview-of-the-state-fire-marshals-office-and-statewide-fire-prevention-code-adoption-process-and-issues.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian McGraw
State Fire Marshal
Virginia Dept. of Fire Programs&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>PEXa Plumbing Systems</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/pexa-plumbing-systems.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-08T11:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-03-08T11:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2017-03-08:/sfpecva/pexa-plumbing-systems.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a joint meeting with local chapter of American Society of Plumbing Engineers (ASPE) The menu will be Beef Stroganoff, Green Beans, Salad, Rolls and Butter, and a dessert plate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Gavin
Systems Engineering Specialist
REHAU&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Arson Investigation</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/arson-investigation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-27T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-27T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2017-02-27:/sfpecva/arson-investigation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Brian Dalrymple has been with the Richmond Fire Department since 2002 and in the fire service since 1998. During his career with the RFD, Brian worked as a firefighter and company officer in several of the department’s specialized rescue teams as well as training incumbent firefighters in the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Brian Dalrymple has been with the Richmond Fire Department since 2002 and in the fire service since 1998. During his career with the RFD, Brian worked as a firefighter and company officer in several of the department’s specialized rescue teams as well as training incumbent firefighters in the department’s training division. He became a member of the department’s Fire and Arson Investigations Unit in 2014 after completing the Virginia Law Enforcement Academy. Lt. Dalrymple and K9 Pearl became partners in 2015 when they trained together for 5 weeks in Maine under the direction of Maine Specialty Dogs and certified under the Maine Criminal Justice Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian Dalrymple
Lieutenant
Richmond Fire - Arson Unit&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Preventing Warehouse Total Loss Caused By Excessive Ventilation</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/preventing-warehouse-total-loss-caused-by-excessive-ventilation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-23T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-23T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2017-01-23:/sfpecva/preventing-warehouse-total-loss-caused-by-excessive-ventilation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The presentation will cover six major warehouse fires where excessive ventilation contributed to a total or near-total loss by causing the fire to accelerate rapidly. It will cover techniques to accomplish the objectives of ventilation without risking rapid fire growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Frank
Loss Prevention Center of Excellence Leader
AXA …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The presentation will cover six major warehouse fires where excessive ventilation contributed to a total or near-total loss by causing the fire to accelerate rapidly. It will cover techniques to accomplish the objectives of ventilation without risking rapid fire growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Frank
Loss Prevention Center of Excellence Leader
AXA XL Risk Consulting&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Residential Fire Sprinkler Systems</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/residential-fire-sprinkler-systems.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-21T16:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-11-21T16:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2016-11-21:/sfpecva/residential-fire-sprinkler-systems.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NFPA 13D, NFA 13R and Light Hazard occupancy protection. Focusing on CPVC compatibility and new residential sprinkler head technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben Johnson&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>Paratherm Heat Transfer Fluids</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/paratherm-heat-transfer-fluids.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-24T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-10-24T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2016-10-24:/sfpecva/paratherm-heat-transfer-fluids.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim Oetinger
Paratherm&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry><entry><title>High Public Occupancy Pre-Emergency Planning</title><link href="https://briancohan.github.io/sfpecva/high-public-occupancy-pre-emergency-planning.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-19T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-19T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Brian Cohan</name></author><id>tag:briancohan.github.io,2016-09-19:/sfpecva/high-public-occupancy-pre-emergency-planning.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new NFPA committee is exploring creation of codes and standards for buildings and facilities with high occupancy loads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presenter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Joseph Kluh
Special Response Team Commander
Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority Police&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Meetings"></category></entry></feed>